Finding Aid for William J. Horvath papers, 1940-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William J. Horvath papers 1940-1985, 1945-1979
Horvath, William J., 1917-
3 linear feet
2011005 Aa 2
William J. Horvath was a specialist and early innovator in the field of operations research. He conducted studies during World War II in undersea and above-water warfare, for which he received several awards. Horvath was a professor of health systems in the University of Michigan's Department of Psychology, and spent much of his career working for the University's Mental Health Research Institute. He was widely respected in his field as an expert in the analysis of health systems. Papers primarily consist of professional correspondence, research, and publications generated throughout his academic and professional career.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was received from Rebecca Horvath in November 2010 (Donor # 10454 )
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William J. Horvath was a specialist in the field of operations research. Lauded for his work on underwater and air warfare during World War II, Horvath continued his career at the University of Michigan, where he served as a professor under the Department of Psychiatry. He also dedicated much of his career to the University's Mental Health Research Institute, where he was a recognized authority on mental health services.
Born in New York City in 1917, William J. Horvath attended, successively, Townsend Harris High School, the City College of New York (CCNY), and New York University (NYU). He received his B.S. from CCNY in 1936, and his M.S. from NYU in 1938 and his Ph.D. from New York University in 1940. His research thesis concerned the measurements of neutrons. He was a University Fellow at NYU from 1937 to 1939, and served concurrently as an instructor in Physics at the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn from 1939 to 1940. Employed by the Bureau of Ordnance, Navy Department as a physicist on problems of mine warfare from 1940 to 1943, Horvath worked under Philip Morse on operations research studies in anti-submarine and air warfare. He later served on both the staffs of Commander Submarine Force Pacific Fleet and the Commander Naval Air Units Pacific Fleet.
During World War II Horvath was a member of the U.S. Navy's Operations Evaluation Group, and later served in a similar capacity to the U.S. Joint Chiefs of Staff. He was in charge of the undersea warfare section from 1946 to 1948, and was Deputy Director of the group in 1949-1950. In 1950 he became a member of the Weapons Systems Evaluation Group in the Joint Chiefs of Staff, where he served as a member of the Review Board for two years.
The years after the war, 1945 to 1949, were spent in helping to organize the Navy's Operations Evaluation Group (OEG) under diverse assignments such as advisor to Assistant Chief of Naval Operations for Undersea Warfare, Operations Research Consultant to Naval Attaché London, England, and finally two years spent as Deputy Director of the OEG Horvath was awarded the Naval Ordnance Development Award and the Presidential Certificate of Merit for his operations research studies in the War, in 1945 and 1947, respectively. He served as a consultant to a number of government agencies on systems problems, as well, working with the Health Services Study Section of the National Institutes of Health in addition to the Health Care Facilities Ad Hoc Advisory Committee of U.S. Public Health Service.
Horvath was a founder and former vice president of the Operations Research Society of America, and served as chairman of the Health Applications Section of the Society. His interest in medical problems began in 1955 when he became Section Head in the Biological and Medical Electronics group of the Airborne Instrument Laboratory. Horvath had a long history working at the Mental Health Research Institute of the University of Michigan, where he worked from 1958 until the late 1980s as a research physicist and scientist, developing mathematical theories of behavior. Appointed professor of health systems in Michigan's Department of Psychiatry in 1972, he also served as the associate director of the University's Health Services Research Center. He became a leader in analysis of health systems at the University of Michigan, conducting studies of health care services delivery, nerve networks, medical diagnosis, and theories of individual and group behavior. In 1977, he initiated the Washtenaw County Health Survey, which has been used as the basis for a number of successful interventions in preventive health behavior.
William Horvath died in 2004.
The papers in this collection document the professional career of William J. Horvath, an expert in the field of operations research. They are divided into seven series: Biographical Information, Correspondence, Operations Research, Operations Research Group, Operations Research Society, Publications, and Research.
Subjects:
Horvath, William J., 1917-; Health services administration.; Mathematical physics.; Operations research.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Mental Health Research Institute.
Contributors:
Flood, Merrill M. (Merrill Meeks), 1908-1991.; Gavin, James M. (James Maurice), 1907-1990.; Morse, Philip M. (Philip McCord), 1903-1985.
- Biographical Information
  The Biographical Information series consists of one folder, which contains documentation pertaining to Horvath's Naval Ordnance Development Award and his Presidential Certificate of Merit. It also includes a single photograph of Horvath.
  - Biographical Information (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Letters contained in the Correspondence series largely represent communication between Horvath and his colleagues, academic peers, and organizations of which he was a member, throughout his professional life. It is the largest series in the collection, spanning a period between 1948 and 1979. Early material includes correspondence between Dr. Horvath and the U.S. government, particularly members of the Allied Forces (post-WWII), the Department of Defense, the Navy, and the Air Force. Also included are invitations to and communications between various honor societies, including the Philosophical Society of Washington and the Cosmos Club.
  The rest of the Correspondence series is largely comprised of papers containing discussions of research with colleagues, various personal letters to and from friends, conversations regarding the exchange of ideas, various requests for reprints of Dr. Horvath's papers, and requests for book and article reviews. Correspondents include James Gavin, Mervill Flood and Philip Morse.
  - 1948-1951 (Box 1)
  - 1952-1955, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1955-1958 (Box 1)
  - April 1958-January 1961, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - January 1961-Decemer 1962, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1961-1964, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1963-1965, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1965-1967, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - March-December 1967, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1968, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1969-1970, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1970, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1973 (Box 2)
  - 1974 (Box 2)
  - 1975 (Box 2)
  - 1976 (Box 2)
  - 1977 (Box 2)
  - 1978 (Box 2)
  - 1979 (Box 2)
- Operations Research
  The Operations Research series consists of notes, reviews of various manuscripts and papers, and correspondence between Horvath and fellow members of the Operational Research Society of America. These papers date from 1961 to 1968.
  - Correspondence 1961-1968, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Notes 1961-1968 (Box 2)
  - Reviews 1961-1968 (Box 2)
- Operations Research Group
  The documents constituting the Operations Research Group series include press releases and articles from 1945 regarding the activities of the Operations Research Group, of which Horvath was a member. The series also contains a biographical sketch of Horvath from 1946.
  - 1945-1946 (Box 2)
- Operations Research Society
  The Operations Research Society series consists of administrative reports, correspondence between members, and organizational information. The papers date from 1954 to 1962.
  - 1954-1955, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1958-1961 (Box 3)
  - 1960-1962 (Box 3)
- Publications and Speeches
  Documents contained in the Publication and Speeches series consist largely of articles and papers appearing in various scientific magazines and journals. A prolific writer, Horvath authored or co-authored many pieces in publications such as The Physical Review, Behavioral Science, and Management Science. The series also includes a set of book reviews from 1957 to 1982, as well as several papers on children's health beliefs from 1980, research reports from MHRI, speeches given at conferences, and other non-attributed articles. The series dates from 1952 to 1982.
  - General (no date) (Box 3)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 3)
  - 1952-1958 (Box 3)
  - 1960-1969, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - 1970-1977, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1980-1985, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Book Reviews 1957-1982 (Box 3)
  - Papers on Children's Health Beliefs, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Research
  The Research series contains three main studies conducted by Dr. Horvath: "Resisting Pressure to Smoke", 1982-1984; WCHS Data, 1982; and Word Associations, 1959-1963.
  - General (Box 3)
  - "Resisting Pressure to Smoke" Study 1982-1984 (Box 3)
  - WCHS Data 1982 (Box 3)
  - Word Associations 1959-1963 (Box 3)